<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached Decemb. 16. 1654. At the funerall of Mr Andrevv Pern, preacher of the Word of God at Wilby in Northampton-shire. By Samuel Ainsworth rector of Kelmarsh.</title>
            <author>Ainsworth, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75990</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A817</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E487_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205454</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864829</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864829</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117061</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75990)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117061)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 77:E487[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached Decemb. 16. 1654. At the funerall of Mr Andrevv Pern, preacher of the Word of God at Wilby in Northampton-shire. By Samuel Ainsworth rector of Kelmarsh.</title>
                  <author>Ainsworth, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Gilberton, and are to be sold by Thomas Collins neare Alhallows Church in Northampton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septem: 22".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Perne, Andrew, 1594-1654.</term>
               <term>Death --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117061:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached <hi>Decemb.</hi> 16. 1654. AT THE FVNERALL OF Mr ANDREVV PERN, Preacher of the Word of God at <hi>Wilby</hi> in <hi>Northampton</hi>-ſhire.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL AINSWORTH</hi> Rector of <hi>Kelmarſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Gilbertſon,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Collins</hi> neare Alhallows Church in <hi>Northampton.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117061:2"/>
            <head>To the Religious, and my much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Aunt, Mrs <hi>Mary Pern,</hi> Grace and peace be multiplied.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare Aunt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E read in the firſt Chapter of <hi>Ruth,</hi> how <hi>Nao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi> a very gracious Matron, loſt first her Husband, and not long after her two Sons: Your condition is not much, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, unlike hers. Your loſſe, in reſpect of your Husband, is not a jot inferiour to hers; her loſſe, in reſpect of her children was greater than yours; ſhe loſt two Sons, you a Daughter only; what difference ſoever there hath been between your loſſes, I ſuppoſe, there is none between your griefes. When you enjoyed both Husband and Child you might well be called <hi>Naomi,</hi> pleaſant, but ſince the wiſe God hath deprived you of them both, the name <hi>Marah,</hi> bitter, hath been more ſutable to your condition, for it hath been ſad and bitter.</p>
            <p>To tell you what a Husband you have lost were but to encreaſe your ſorrow, which I feare needs ſtopping rather than venting; I ſhall therefore obſerve that courſe which was uſed by the Iews, who when their deare friends, or neighbours, had loſt either Husband or Wife, Father or Child, they brought them a cup of conſolation for to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them, <hi>Jer. 16.7.</hi> The Prophet <hi>David</hi> tels us,
<pb facs="tcp:117061:3"/>
               <hi>Pſal. 119.50.</hi> That the word of God was his comfort in his affliction; and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> labours to ſupport the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> for the loſſe of their Chriſtian friends by ſetting the word of God before them, <hi>1 Theſ. 4.18.</hi> Theſe following Scriptures therefore are the cup of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation with which I ſhall preſent you to mitigate your too much abounding ſorrow, <hi>Prov. 3.12. Whom the Lord loveth he correcteth, even as a father the ſon in whom he delighteth.</hi> Rom. <hi>8.28. We know all things worke together for good to them that love God, to them who are the called according to his purpoſe.</hi> Iſa. <hi>27.9. By this therefore ſhall the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of</hi> Iacob <hi>be purged,</hi> and this is all the fruit, to take away his ſin, <hi>Heb. 12.10, 11. For they verily for a few daies chaſtened us after their own pleaſure, but he for our profit, that we might be partakers of his holineſſe. Now no chaſtening for the preſent ſeems to be joyous but grievous: nevertheleſs afterwards it yeeldeth the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſs unto them which are exerciſed thereby,</hi> Iſa. <hi>54.5. Thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker is thy husband,</hi> Pſal. <hi>146.9. The Lord preſerveth the ſtrangers, he releeveth the fatherleſs and widdow.</hi> Now if God hath taken away your deare husband and child out of love to your ſoule; if their naturall deaths ſhall promote your ſpirituall life; if their taking up to heaven ſhall prepare and make you fitter for heaven; if their loſſe ſhall be your gaine, the purging away of your droſſe, and the making of you a more refined veſſell for your Maſters uſe, the weakning of your corruptions, and the ſtrengthning of your graces; if God will be a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to you, whoſe love is more pure, ſtrong, raviſhing, ſatisfying, and durable than the love of the beſt husband that ever breath'd upon earth; if God will be preſent
<pb facs="tcp:117061:3"/>with you, in whoſe preſence is fulneſſe of joy, and take care of you, to protect and counſell, to help and releeve you, be your enemies and dangers what they will; Have you not more cauſe to rejoyce in theſe ſpirituall priviledges than to mourne for your temporall loſſes? Take therefore the counſell of the Apoſtle, <hi>1 Theſ. 4.18.</hi> Comfort your ſelfe in the meditation of theſe Scriptures. Do as <hi>David</hi> did when he had loſt all at <hi>Ziglag,</hi> encourage your ſelfe in the Lord your God, <hi>1 Sam. 30.6.</hi> Although Ciſterns fail, yet God is a fountaine that cannot be drawn dry; when the Creature neither is nor can be the ſame to us, yet God is the ſame, yeſterday, and to day, and for ever, <hi>Heb. 13.8.</hi> Now that the God of all grace and conſolation would make up your loſſes by the abundant ſupplies of his bleſſed Spirit, ſanctifie his correcting hand unto you, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port you under your heavy burden, and fit you with all joy and peace in beleeving, is the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſympathizing and much obliged kinſman, SAMUEL AINSVVORTH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:117061:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117061:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Kings 13.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now <hi>Eliſha</hi> was fallen ſick of his ſickneſſe whereof he died, and <hi>Joaſh</hi> the King of Iſrael came down unto him and wept over his face, and ſaid, O my father, my father, the Chariot of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe words we may take notice of theſe two generall parts:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſickneſſe, wherin we may conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who this <hi>Eliſha</hi> was, he was not only a holy man, but a holy Prophet.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The event of his ſickneſſe, ſick he was, and that unto death, and died of this his ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Joaſh's</hi> viſiting of him in this his ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who this <hi>Joaſh</hi> was who came to viſit him, no mean perſon, no plaine country man, no poore neighbour, but a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117061:5"/>man of eminent place and dignity, he was no leſſe than a King, and King of Iſrael.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The paines he took to viſit him; he did not take a ſtep or two to ſee the Prophet. <hi>Eliſha</hi> was now no neere neighbour, he was either at <hi>Jericho,</hi> or at <hi>Bethel,</hi> or in ſome other place remote from <hi>Samaria,</hi> the uſuall ſeat of the Kings of Iſrael, and from whence <hi>Joaſh</hi> came down to viſit him. It had been no ſmall favour for ſo great a Prince to have ſent one of his choice favourites upon this errand, and to have ſtaied at home himſelfe, but he thought it not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to diſpatch his ſervant with a How do you: but waits upon the poore Prophet in his own perſon; he queſtions it not whether it would not be too great a condeſcenſion for his excellent Majeſty to ſee how ſo meane a ſubject did; he made no ſcruple whether his diſeaſe might not be noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, or infectious, he waved theſe things, ſtood not upon his magnificency, but makes a journey himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The motive that prevailed with him to viſit this man of God, which makes the action more commendable, it was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but that reſpect which he did beare unto him. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi> had been a great friend to the State, ſecured it againe and againe againſt the incurſions of the <hi>Syrians,</hi> procured wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the Armies of Iſrael when they were in danger to periſh for want of it; aſſured them of the great victory that they ſhould obtaine againſt the <hi>Ammonites;</hi> helpt them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo when they were at a dead lift by his prayers; theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy acts were remembred by this King, who honoured the Prophet for them, and expreſt what high thoughts he had of him by giving of him ſuch a friendly and honourable vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. <hi>Ahab,</hi> the Predeceſſor of <hi>Joaſh,</hi> though not immediately, would never have ſhewed ſuch kindneſſe to <hi>Elijah</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor of <hi>Eliſha;</hi> he would rather have been glad of, then viſited him in his ſickneſſe. <hi>David</hi> complaines of ſome who came to him in the day of his calamity, when he was under ſome grievous diſeaſe, not to comfort him, but to ſee whether there was any hope of his death; but <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſh,</hi> though a wicked man, viſited not the Prophet upon ſuch an account, he deſired his life, and feared his death;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117061:5"/>he came not out of hatred, but out of love; not to entrap him, but to comfort him; not to obſerve whether there were any hopes of his death, but whether there were any hopes of his life; not as a malicious ſpy, to watch whether any words dropt from his lips which he might ſpread abroad to his reproach, but as a friend to condole and ſympathize with him, and to bemoane ſo great a loſſe; for when he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that he was drawing nigh unto his end, and ere long would bid that Kingdome and the world farewell, he wept over his face.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The honourable titles which he gave unto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet not in a falſe and flattering complement (the common ſin of this Age, wherein men profeſſe that with their lips which is far from their hearts,) but from a juſt and a reall ſenſe and apprehenſion that he had of the Prophets me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and deſerts, to be honoured with the title of Father, and to be accounted and eſteemed the Chariot of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof: And he ſaid, <hi>O my father, my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c.</hi> The parts thus opened, we come to the Doctrines which ariſe out of the words. The perſon that was ſick and died, we told you was both a good man, and a holy Prophet, from whence we may obſerve in the firſt place:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>
               </label> That the beſt of men muſt dye, neither great nor good can eſcape deaths dart. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.48. <hi>What man is he that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth and ſhall not ſee death?</hi> The wiſe as well as the fooliſh, the pious as well as the impious, the ſtrict as well as the looſe muſt lye down in the grave. <hi>Pallida mors aequo pulſat pede pauperum tabernas regumque turres. Abraham,</hi> eminent for faith; <hi>Moſes,</hi> for meekneſſe; <hi>David,</hi> for zeale; <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat,</hi> for livelineſſe and holy fervour in the waies of God; <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> for ſpirituall valour and courage: yet they all ſhut their eyes upon the world, and bad it farewell. Look upon thoſe worthies made mention of, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. men of whom the world was not worthy, what became of them? The Text tels us, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. All theſe died in the faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Firſt, The bodies of the beſt are compoſed of the ſame materials with the bodies of the worſt; the gracious ſoule hath no ſtronger a Cabinet than the graceleſſe ſoule; good
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117061:6"/>men many times have weaker bodies than bad men. <hi>Gaius</hi> who had a thriving ſoule, had a weake and ſickly body; the beſt are but earthen veſſels at the beſt,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.7.</note> which will not laſt alwaies, but lye open to a thouſand caſualties, and a little knock breakes them in peeces.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.2, 3.</note> Chriſt hath prepared a better place for them, to which they muſt paſſe through the gates of death; this the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> knew full well,
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> and therefore he deſired to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt. He tels us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. that he was willing that mortality might be ſwallowed up of life; loath he was to be uncloathed, but yet he choſe to be ſtript by death of his old rags, rather than not to be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with thoſe robes which he expected from heaven.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.24.</note> Chriſt hath prayed that they might be where he is, therefore they muſt not live here alwaies. We read, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.2. that the heavens muſt receive Chriſt till the times of reſtitution of all things. Though Chriſt, as God, is every where, yet as he is Mediator he ſits at the right hand of his Father. Now there is no being where Chriſt is without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the cup of death, whereof Chriſt himſelfe taſted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was taken up into glory. Chriſts members muſt be conformable unto him in ſuffering death here, before they can be made conformable unto him in glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God loves them ſo well, that he will have them come home unto him; here gracious ſoules are ſaid to be abſent from the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. as children long to ſee their beloved Parents, ſo loving Parents long to have the full enjoyment of their Children. Chriſt can no more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure that his Children ſhould be alwaies from him, than his Children can endure to be alwaies from Chriſt. Now the ordinary meſſenger which Chriſt imploies to bring home his Children unto him is death. <hi>Uſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Muſt the righteous dye? what then ſhall become of the unrighteous? Will God make his own to drinke of this bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cup? Then let not thoſe, who are none of Gods, thinke to eſcape it; no, no, dye, dye you muſt, though full ſore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your wills; But ſhall your deaths be like unto the deaths of Gods holy ones? No: there ſhall be as great a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117061:6"/>difference between your deaths and theirs, as there hath been between your lives and theirs; they are taken away from the evill to come, but your evill is to come when you are taken away; they are taken away from their enemies, but go to their friends; you are taken away from your friends, but muſt go to your enemies; they are taken away in mercy, you ſhall be taken away in judgement; when they dye, they go to heaven; when you dye, you muſt go to hell; when they dye, they go to enjoy ſweet and uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted communion with Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; when you dye, you muſt go to converſe with devils &amp; damned ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; when they dye, their worſt is paſt, their beſt is to come, when you dye, your beſt is paſt, your worſt is to come; when they dye, they ſhall ſuffer no more, you never ſuffer to any purpoſe till you come to dye: Now, now you ſhall be ſnatch'd from your cups of pleaſure to drinke of cups of gall and wormwood;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> from your ſtately houſes to a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome dungeon; from your carnall eaſe and contentments to endleſſe and extreme tortures and howlings. Woe, woe unto you wicked ones, weep and howle for the miſeries which are likely to come upon you, you are not ſo high now but you will be as low then, you are not ſo honourable now but you will be as contemptible then, you are not ſo joviall and merry now but you will be as ſad and heavy then; would you dye as the righteous dye, then live as the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous live; if you would have your latter end like unto his, let your converſation for the preſent be like unto his.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Muſt good men, very good men, the beſt of men, ſuch who have received a double portion of the ſpirit more than others, who are full of faith and of the Holy Ghoſt, dye? Then let this teach us to make ſure of God, who lives for ever, and cannot dye; great is the comfort, much is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit which is conveighed from perſons eminent for grace and heavenly wiſdome unto thoſe who depend upon them, and converſe with them; they are lights to guide, they are fires to warme, they are cordials to comfort, they are Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours to inſtruct ſuch as are round about them; what a choice mercy is a pious husband to his wife, a godly father
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117061:7"/>to his children, a religious maſter to his ſervant, and a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous neighbour to his neighbours, much ſpirituall advantage may be, and is, reaped by their prayers, counſels, experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and examples; how often have our dead hearts been quickned, our doubts reſolved, our feares ſcattered, our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows mitigated, and our graces excited by converſing and diſcourſing with pious and holy men; they carry about them very choice and precious liquor, but it is contained in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then veſſels which muſt and will break; the time will come when the godly Husband, when the pious Maſter, when the gracious Parent muſt tarry with us no longer, when we ſhall have no more of their counſell to inſtruct us, no more of their encouragements to provoke us, no more of their prayers to help us, thoſe ciſternes muſt be broken, and let this conſideration put us upon the ſecuring of the fountaine, that when thoſe earthen veſſels are ſnapt in peeces, when thoſe pipes, through which God conveyed much ſweetneſs and benefit to thy ſoule, are taken away, thou maieſt have this to comfort thee, that the fountaine, that can never be drawn dry, is ſtill with thee; if God be thine thou art well, though others can no more be enjoyed in the land of the living; God is a husband that cannot dye, a father that cannot dye, a ſhepheard that cannot dye, a friend that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dye; all other can do nothing without him, he can do any thing without others; he can comfort, he can quicken, he can ſupport, he can ſtrengthen, he can uphold us though we had not one friend in the world left us; he is God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, and can make up the loſſe of a husband to the wife, of a father to the child, of a paſtor to his people: Oh then make ſure of God for your God, you cannot ſo make ſure of any creature, friends, or comforters, as to keep and enjoy them alwaies, they will be gone from you, but you may make ſure of God; get God, and you want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, want God, and you have nothing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Muſt the beſt dye? then let us prepare for their death; we ſeldome thinke of croſſes till they come, and then we are to ſeek for patience for to beare them: what heare we? little did I think that I ſhould have ſeen this day, that I ſhould
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117061:7"/>have been bereaved of my husband, ſaith the wife; little did I thinke that I ſhould have loſt ſo precious a father, ſaith the child; and why did you not think ſo? <hi>Job</hi> lookt for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity in the midſt of proſperity, for loſſes in the midſt of enjoyments; he lookt upon his children as mortall,
<note place="margin">Iob 3.25.</note> his goods as uncertaine, he feared, and fore-thought of thoſe troubles which he met withall; and hence it was he bore them with ſo much patience; God hath not given us a leaſe of his childrens lives, it is a mercy, and a great one, that he will truſt us with the ſight or preſence of thoſe his jewels,
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note> though but for a ſeaſon; wives look upon your precious husbands, children look upon your gracious parents as bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that ſwim up and down in the water for a while, but ere long will vaniſh.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Muſt godly men dye? let us improve them whileſt we have them: if we have but a book lent us, which we account very profitable, and know it may be call'd for at an houres warning, we will make the beſt uſe we can of it whileſt we have it; our chriſtian friends are but lent us, how ſoon our heavenly Father may ſend for them we know not, let us therefore make the beſt advantage that may be of their graces and vertues during their abode with us;
<note place="margin">Chap. 3.16</note> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Malachy</hi> tels us, they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another; God betruſts us with his deare ſervants that we might promote our ſpirituall warfare by their ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and will call us to an account one day how we have thrived by ſuch helps; Let a Lawyer come to our houſes, we will aske him queſtion after queſtion about our tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eſtate, what, have we no queſtions to propound in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to our ſpirituall eſtate? Surely then we are ignorant or inſenſible. Haſt thou a gracious husband? Let no day paſſe over thy head without reaping ſome ſpirituall good by him. Haſt thou a gracious neighbour? Improve his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany for thy ſoules benefit. How rich might Chriſtians be in grace, had they but skill and will to improve one another? Now you may have the benefit of their prayers, counſels, gifts, experiences, but they can do nothing for you in the grave. Our wofull negligence to improve our Chriſtian
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117061:8"/>friends makes God many times to deprive us of them, we might have enjoyed them longer had we been carefull to make better uſe of them; when ſervants rather play with, then worke by the light, it is time to put it out. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take the counſell of our Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.35.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let all holy and gracious perſons be active for God whileſt they live, let ſlip no opportunity of doing God ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, we have received much from, and ſhall we not do much for God? God thinkes nothing too great for us, let not us think any thing too great for God; work we as hard as we can, our wages will infinitely ſurpaſſe our worke. Let no man be idle in his Maſters Vineyard, for our labour ſhall not be in vaine in the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. when we caſt our eyes upon our Wives, Children, Neighbours, Servants, or Friends, thinke we may be taken from them ere long, and let this provoke us to do our beſt to leave their ſoules full of grace, though we may have little elſe to leave them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Muſt our beſt friends dye? Will God gather up his Jewels, and deck his own glorious palace with them? Take we heed of murmuring or repining, poſſeſſe vve our ſoules in patience, bleſſe God that he hath truſt us vvith them ſo long, complaine not that he hath taken them avvay ſo ſoon; they are deare to God as vvell as unto us, and ought vve not to be content that God ſhould enjoy them as vvell as vve? When vve ſee Gods vvill fulfilled, it is not for us ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to quarrell, but quietly and patiently to ſubmit. Thus did <hi>Aaron, Lev.</hi> 10.3. Thus did <hi>Eli,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 3.18. Thus did <hi>Job, Chap.</hi> 1. Thus did <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 39.9. True, vve are lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,
<note place="margin">14.28.</note> but our godly friends are gainers, love to our ſelves may make us mourne, but love to them ſhould make us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce: Ought vve not to be, and are vve not glad vvhen our friends vvho have been full of paine enjoy ſvveet eaſe? vvho have been in priſon are ſet at liberty? vvho have been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed and oppreſſed by cruell, potent, and malicious enemies, are delivered from them? And is not this the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all our gracious friends vvhen they dye? Are they not novv at eaſe vvho vvere once in paine? Are they not novv at liberty vvho vvere once in priſon? For this vvorld
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117061:8"/>is a priſon to a pious ſoule. Are they not novv freed from all their enemies, vvho could have no reſt night or day from one enemy or other? Rejoice therefore that their vvarfare is accompliſhed, and bleſſe God that he hath not taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay himſelfe from us, though he hath deprived us of ſuch vvho vvere our deare friends, vve have no cauſe to grudge at the loſſe of theſe Ciſternes ſo long as vve have the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. What though theſe bottles be dry, vve cannot vvant the refreſhing vvaters of comfort ſo long as the ſpring is vvith us; vvhen God takes avvay our outvvard helps, he takes avvay ſuch as may better be ſpared than himſelfe; let our loſſes be what they vvill, they may very vvell be borne ſo long as vve enjoy God, vvho is alſufficient. Haſt thou loſt a loving husband, yet bleſſe God that Chriſt vvho loves thee, and will live vvith thee, is not loſt; thy naturall Father is dead, but thou haſt a Father in heaven vvho vvants no vviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to counſell thee, no love to comfort thee, no povver to help thee, no ſupplies to relieve thee, vvho is not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or unſenſible of thy condition, and vvill be vvith thee continually. Thou haſt loſt a precious Paſtor, yet thou haſt a better ſhepheard to take care of thee, the Lord Jeſus bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever.</p>
            <p>But vvhy ſay I, vve have loſt our friends vvhen they dye? We rather part vvith them for a ſeaſon than loſe them: they are gone a little before us to that place vvhere vve ſhall be ere long, and enjoy them more refined, more pure, more lovely and amiable, never to part vvith them more. Beſides, vve have cauſe to rejoyce, though not in the death of our Chriſtian friends, yet in the ſpirituall benefits that vve ſhall reap by their deaths; God hath ſaid,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> All things ſhall vvorke together for good to thoſe vvho love him, and are the called according to his purpoſe. True, vve cannot ſee hovv the loſſe of gracious friends ſhall turn to our advantage, but vve muſt ſhut the eyes of ſenſe, and live by faith in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, it is ground ſufficient for us to beleeve that vve ſhall be gainers by our loſſes, becauſe God hath ſaid ſo, vvho can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lye.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Muſt godly men dye? Then let godly men take heed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117061:9"/>of ſetting their hearts inordinately upon theſe outward bleſſings and comforts, from which they muſt part; the more the world is in our affections, the leſſe pleaſing and welcome will the thoughts of death be unto us. Why are we loath to dye? Becauſe we are not prepared; and why are we not prepared? But becauſe we have minded earth too much, and heaven too little. Oh the world, the world! how hath it got too much hold of the hearts of too many good Chriſtians; never was there more need to preach upon that Text, <hi>Take heed and beware of covetouſneſſe;</hi> Or upon thoſe words of <hi>Paul, Set your affections upon things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, not on things below.</hi> What heare we from the men of the world? For ought we ſee, theſe who pretend ſo much to heaven are as greedy after the earth as others, and it were well if their tongues were no flander in this particular; if the world be our treaſure, why make we a profeſſion of Chriſt? And if Chriſt be our treaſure, why do we embrace the world? It is no wonder to ſee earnall men, who have not God for their Father, who have no promiſe for a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſupply of thoſe outward things, who have no ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſtock to comfort their hearts, no heaven but what may be found in the confluence of temporall enjoyments, to be violent in their deſires and endeavours after the world; but you that are Chriſtians indeed, and not in name only, have no cauſe to be over-carefull, or to cumber your ſelves with too many things. Gods power and faithfulneſſe are engaged that you ſhall want no good thing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. Grant you have wife and children to provide for, yet take heed of wounding your own ſoules and conſciences by exceſſive thoughtfulneſſe for their bodies; the Apoſtles rule muſt be obeyed, or elſe we ſhall be found guilty; but what is that you will ſay? read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29.30, 31. the beſt way we can take to provide for wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren is, to do what God commands, and not to practice what God forbids, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.1, 2, 3. As I would not have you to neglect your particular callings, ſo I would not have you to forget your generall callings: thinke not only that you are men, and ſtand in need of earthly ſupplies, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117061:9"/>remember alſo you are Chriſtians, and are call'd to have your converſation in heaven, be you thoughtfull to honour God, and God will be thoughtfull to maintaine and provide for you and yours. Walke therefore cloſely with God, keep up and maintaine the power of Godlineſſe, improve all opportunities put into your hands to do, or to get good, balke no duty commanded. Be more mindfull to make thy friends and children good than great, and to leave them in the armes of Chriſt, than to leave them millions of gold and ſilver. An eſtate raiſed by ſinfull neglects or commiſſions will do thy children more hurt than good, and it is more than an even lay, that that will be ſpent looſely by them, which hath been gotten covetouſly by thee.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Muſt the godly dye? Then let thoſe who are godly prepare for death; do nothing now which may move God to conceale his love in that laſt houre. True it is, no ſooner ſhall your breath be ſtopt here, but your ſoules ſhall be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into heaven; yet you may ſo order the matter, that your departure may be clouded. Ah! how ſweet will it be for God to ſmile upon us when we come to dye, to ſay unto us, <hi>Well done thou good and faithfull ſervant, enter now into thy Maſters joy.</hi> Give all diligence to make your Calling and Election ſure; keep your evidences cleare, blot them not by any looſe or ſcandalous practice, take heed of grieving that ſpirit which hath at any time ſealed you to the day of redemption.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Muſt the godly dye? Let this be matter of ſupport and conſolation unto all godly ones in the midſt of thoſe troubles and temptations which they meet withall in the world; Art thou buffeted by ſathans temptations, wearied with that body of death which thou carrieſt about thee? Doſt thou groane under the burden of a vile and curſed heart? Art thou followed with variety of afflictions? Do thy enemies ſcorne and perſecute thee? Be of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, death will come, death will come ere long, and ſet thee free from all thine enemies. <hi>Job,</hi> ſpeaking of the grave, tels us, There the wicked ceaſe from troubling, there the weary are at reſt. <hi>Job</hi> 3.17. Thus we have done with the firſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117061:10"/>Doctrine; in the next place we ſhall look upon <hi>Eliſha</hi> as a holy Prophet, and from hence give you this obſervation,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> That ſuch Miniſters who are very uſefull and holy muſt dye. <hi>Eliſha</hi> a moſt gracious Prophet, furniſhed with a double portion of that ſpirit which acted in his Maſter <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah,</hi> a moſt uſefull man; the Chariot and the horſemen of Iſrael muſt not live alwaies, but give up the Ghoſt. For proofe of the Doctrine conſult with theſe Scriptures though we have had many ſad experiences, and that of late to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25 1. What is become of all the Apoſtles who ſerved God in their generation, were ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Fathers to beget ſoules unto God, who both planted and builded up the Church of God, who were choice and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious men, one was crucified, another headed, another boiled in a Cauldron, and all died? Where is our <hi>Preſton,</hi> our <hi>Taylor,</hi> our <hi>Sibs,</hi> our <hi>Hill,</hi> our <hi>Whitaker,</hi> and many more? The grave hath ſwallowed them up. The reaſons which we gave you to prove the precedent Doctrine might ſerve for the confirmation of this, but we will adde one or two more.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe people will not make that uſe of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry as they ſhould; God ſends them to negotiate a peace between his glorious Majeſty and peoples precious ſoules: Now when they have made many overtures from their great Lord and Maſter, and all are ſlighted, none will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, God thinkes it fit to ſend for them home; when Princes ſee that Embaſſadours cannot obtaine with For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign States what they expected, they call them home again; there are not more uſefull inſtruments in a State, or Church, than faithfull and holy Miniſters, God ſets them up as lights to enlighten the minds of men, as guides to direct men, as watchmen to warne them, as ſaviours to deliver them out of the hands of their enemies, Sin, Sathan, and the World: Now, if no body will make uſe of their light, follow their directions, regard their warnings, or be willing to be reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened out of the hands of their ſpirituall enemies, it is but juſt with God to take them away: <hi>Who hath beleeved our report,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>and to whom is the arme of the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117061:10"/> 2. God will not ſuffer his Miniſters alwaies to live in the world, becauſe the world is not worthy of them, they are ſo far from improving their doctrine and life, that they are rather filled with rage againſt them both; the Scripture ſpeakes much of the worlds unkind and perverſe carriage towards the Meſſengers of God; read theſe places, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16. <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.16. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.7, 8. <hi>Micah</hi> 2.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37. by abuſing mercies we juſtly forfeit them. The world is weary of Gods Miniſters, and Gods Miniſters are weary of the world; now God will eaſe the world of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and when he doth this, it is in wrath to the world; and he will eaſe his Miniſters of the world, but when he doth this, it is in mercy to his Miniſters; God is very tender of his Meſſengers, takes the ſcornes and affronts caſt upon them as offered unto himſelf, he cannot endure to ſee them wrong'd, and hence it is that he will remove them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Should the Miniſters of God live here alwaies, none would be ſo miſerable as they are, did not their future hopes ſupport them their preſent condition would be very ſad; though all that live godly in Chriſt ſuffer perſecution, yet none ſo perſecuted as the godly Miniſters, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19 other Chriſtians may drinke of bitter cups, but the dregs uſually are poured on the Lords Embaſſadours, if others endure a ſtorm, yet the fierceſt part lights upon them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Die they muſt, that they may receive that Crown of righteouſneſſe which God hath laid up for them in heaven; the Crown of life will not be ſet upon their heads, till they have paſſed through the ſtraights of death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2, 3. Uſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It ſhould teach us that are Gods Miniſters, to do what we can for God whileſt we have time and ſtrength; How active was the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> when he perceived a doore was opened to promote the intereſt of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? He knew not how long that doore might ſtand open, nor how ſoone he might be taken away, and this made him to beſtirre himſelfe the more; when he perceived that his departure drew nigh, he ſends for the Elders of <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.</note> and beſtows his counſels and prayers upon them. The
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117061:11"/>Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> alſo, underſtanding that he had not long to live, was the more carefull to ſtir up the minds of the diſperſed Jews to keep the faith that had been delivered unto them, and to grow in grace and in the knowledge of Chriſt, and to take heed that they were not carried away with the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the wicked, and ſo fall from their own ſtedfaſtneſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13, 14. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.17, 18. Take we therefore the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Solomon, Eccl.</hi> 9.10. Let our thoughts and our ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, our prayers, and our counſels, our time and our ſtrength be laid out for our Lord and Maſter. Let that which a godly Miniſter wrote upon his Study doore be deeply engraven in our memories, and thought upon every day by us, <hi>Miniſter verbi es, hoc age.</hi> Let us be more mindfull of our work than of our wages, how to encreaſe Chriſts Kingdome, than to advance our own ſecular intereſts, how to make our people good, than how to render our ſelves great, how to enrich the ſoules of others, rather than to be enriched by others; we have a good Maſter that will pay us well,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 52, 3.4.</note> and though we ſhould have little encouragement from the ungratefull world, yet we ſhall want no encouragement from our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God. Oh that the ſame mind were in us which was in Jeſus Chriſt, who ſought not his own honour, but the honour of him that ſent him. We know not how ſoone we may be laid aſide, let us worke, the harder whileſt we have time.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Muſt Gods faithfull Miniſters die, yet do you take heed of having any hand in their deaths; precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints, but the death of no Saints is more precious in Gods ſight than the death of his Miniſters; <hi>Were you not afraid,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam, to ſpeake againſt my ſervant</hi> Moſes? one who was ſo neere unto God; much more cauſe have we to feare to act againſt them; if God was ſo angry vvith thoſe vvho did ſtrike them vvith their tongues, hovv angry vvill he be vvith thoſe vvho ſtrike them vvith their hands? That counſell vvhich <hi>Pilates</hi> Wife gave him, in reference to the Lord Jeſus, will not be amiſſe for any to take in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his Miniſters and ſervants, you may read it,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117061:11"/>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.19. Have no phyſicall hand in their death, have no morall hand in their death, provoke not God by your ſins to deprive you of their labours, the lengthning out of their lives may be the lengthning out of yours, and their deaths may make way for yours, you will be the greateſt loſers, they undoubtedly will be gainers, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23, 24. They are your watchmen, if they be removed, ſpoylers may quickly breake in upon you; they are your guides, if they die, you may ſoon ſtep into by-paths; they ſtand between God and you that judgement might be kept off, that mercies might be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued; if they fall to the earth, it will not be long ere wrath will fall upon you. Be ſo kind and loving to your ſelves, as not to be unkind or cruell towards them, leſt you haſten their deaths whoſe prayers and teares preſerve your lives. Slight not that counſell which they deliver you from God; oppoſe not thoſe truths which they bring ſtampt with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine authority, turne not your backs upon their Miniſtry, or that Miniſtry which they have received from the Lord; ſet not up, nor abet, nor countenance any factions againſt them; let there be no diviſions, no ſeparations, which have not Gods allowance and approbation; let not your lives be looſe and ſcandalous, give them not cauſe to ſay, we have laboured in vaine, we have ſpent our ſtrength in vaine, theſe things will pierce the hearts of gracious Miniſters, and bring them with ſorrow to their graves, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Jer</hi> 9.1. as your cloſe walking will be their joy, ſo your carnall wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king will be their grief; what faithful ſervant will not mourn to ſee his Maſters errant ſlighted and contemned? As it is a dreadfull thing for Miniſters to be guilty of the bloud of their peoples ſoules by any curſed neglect, ſo it is a dreadfull thing for people to be guilty of the bloud of their Miniſters by their ungodly and unwarrantable practices.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Muſt godly Miniſters dye? make uſe then of them whileſt you have them; let a phyſician come to your houſe, but for an houre or two, and you will aske him all that you can thinke of which may be conducible to your bodily health; Do the Prophets live for ever? Here they have no abiding place, they are every day upon removing, ſuffer
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117061:12"/>them not to go to heaven without receiving ſome ſpirituall good from them, get ſome benefit by that precious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor which is in them, before the earthen veſſels that carry it be broken in peeces; they are given you to make you bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, all their gifts, all their graces, all their abilities are yours, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.23. when <hi>Eliſha</hi> underſtood that his maſter <hi>Elijah</hi> would ere long be taken from his head, he would not leave him one moment, but was carefull to improve him to the utmoſt; how gladly would we be inſtruments of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, helpers of your faith, furtherers of your joy, every way promoters of your ſpirituall welfare? How willingly would we ſpend our ſelves, and be ſpent for you? Oh that you were but as deſirous to receive good from us, as we are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to do good to you; God knows how earneſt we are that Chriſt may be formed in you before we go hence and be no more ſeene; take the counſell which our Saviour Chriſt gave his hearers, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.35. improve Gods Miniſters in publike, be conſtant and diligent hearers of them, receive the Law at their mouths; let not their counſels be as water ſpilt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground which cannot be gathered up; let them not have cauſe to complaine as <hi>Simon Peter</hi> did, <hi>Luke</hi> 5.4. that they have caſt the net Sabbath after Sabbath but have caught nothing: Improve them in private, conferre often with them, how glad would we be of your company, we are willing to give you our counſell without the expectation of a fee, improve their experiences; our temptations, our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.4.</note> our buffetings, our trials, in a word, all our expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences are for your advantage: we are exerciſed with doubts, feares, deſertions, aſſaults, that we may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to ſpeake a word in ſeaſon unto you: God hath lent you a pious and a painfull Miniſter for 27 yeares, he hath preached the word amongſt you, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; oh turne your eyes inward, and examine your ſelves how you have improved him, for God will examine you one day; if any of you after ſo much plowing, dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, dunging, ſtill remaine barren, let me tell you you are neere unto curſing; if thoſe multiplied ſhoures of divine truths, which have fallen amongſt you, have not bettered
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117061:12"/>you,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.14, 15.</note> your condemnation at that great day will be greater than the condemnation of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Muſt uſefull and godly Miniſters die? Yet let us keep them as long as we can; we will do what we can to preſerve the lives of thoſe who are inſtruments of much good unto us, we have more cauſe to ſeek the ſafety and continuance of our ſoule-friends than of the friends of our bodies; ſpirituall welfare is better than corporall, and a thriving ſoule than a proſperous eſtate; God hath leſſened the number of able and gracious Miniſters very much of late; many burning and ſhining Lights have been extinguiſhed: call we upon God to ſtay his hand, leſt we be overſpread with darkneſſe, let them not dye for want of our prayers and teares to keep them alive. <hi>Peter</hi> was nigh unto death, the Church praies for him, and God gave her <hi>Peters</hi> life as an anſwer to her prayers, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.12, 13. Take heed alſo of ſlighting, ſcorning, and abuſing of the Miniſters of God, nothing provokes God more to deprive us of his bleſſings, than our wretched undervaluing and abuſing of them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37. Jeſuiticall deſignes are on foot, to lay aſide and root out Gods faithfull Meſſengers; never was there grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cauſe of feare, that what hath often been attempted ſhall now be put into execution; thoſe revilings and contempts which have been, and ſtill are caſt upon the Miniſtry with too much countenance from ſome, and without any check from others, may incenſe God to put out thoſe lights that are as yet ſhining, and to give way to the curſed enterprizes and machinations of men of corrupt minds and malicious and prophane hearts. Againe, would we have God to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue our Teachers unto us? would we ſee their faces ſtill? and not have them driven into corners? let us be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full under their Miniſtry, anſwer the paines and coſt they are at with us; God will not grudge any kindneſſe to a ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriving people, the barrenneſſe of hearers will cauſe a dearth and ſcarcity of Preachers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. You will not ſuffer your ſervants to ſpend their time alwaies in ploughing, dreſſing, and ſowing that ground, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all your labour brings forth nothing but briars
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117061:13"/>and thornes; God will call away his Miniſters from thoſe places where they have beſtowed much paines, but cannot prevaile with their people to be a jot better. Againe, would you ſee the faces of your Teachers ſtill? Bleſſe God for them; unthankfulneſſe deprives us of many choice favours; we live in ſad times, Gods Meſſengers are lookt upon as the burdens of the Nation, but had the Nation no worſe burdens, they would have no cauſe to groane or complaine; ſome there are who once thought themſelves happy in the enjoyment of a faithfull Paſtor, who now would thinke themſelves happy in the want and loſſe of him; God may let ſuch men have their ſuppoſed happineſſe, take away ſuch a Miniſter from them, but it will prove a reall miſery; who would not exclaime againſt that child who ſhould be weary of a moſt gracious and loving Father? and yet how many, who look upon themſelves as converted, who are weary of their ſpirituall Fathers, are ſo far from bleſſing God for them, that they would rather bleſſe God ſhould they be rid of them? Well, God may eaſe you of them ſoone enough, though you care not for their company, he doth, though you ſlight them, yet God highly eſteems of them: Are there not thoſe who are ready to ſay of the Miniſters of Chriſt as they did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.4. of the Jews, Let us cut them off from the Nation, that the name of Miniſters may be had no more in remembrance; God may grant ſuch men what they would have, not in mercy, but in wrath, as he gave the Iſraelites quailes, and a King, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.31. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13 11. Would we enjoy Gods Meſſengers amongſt us: let us be thankfull for them, not fretfull againſt them; let us eſteeme them very highly in love, and not proſecute and perſecute them with extreame malice and hatred.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Muſt godly and painefull Miniſters die? Then let us prepare for their death; make ſure of that Prophet who cannot die but lives for ever, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; ſhould all the Miniſters in a Country be taken away from thee, or you ſhut up in ſome priſon from them, Chriſt can abundantly ſupply their abſence and loſſe. <hi>John</hi> told the people, he baptized them with water, but Chriſt would
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117061:13"/>baptize them with the Holy Ghoſt; Alas we can but ſpeake to your eares, it is Chriſt who muſt ſpeake to your hearts: It were a dreadfull ſin for any man to turne his back upon the Miniſtry of the word when he hath liberty to attend upon it; but if God ſhall be pleaſed to remove his Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, and to take away his Miniſters, we may hope (Chriſt being ours) that he will ſupply the abſence of his ſervants. Chriſt doth not make uſe of Miniſters out of an abſolute neceſſity, as if he could not teach or comfort without them, but out of choice. Againe, get the ſpirit of the Lord Jeſus: Other lights may and muſt be put out, but this will be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and permanent, when other guides are gone, this will continue and abide with us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.16, 17, 18. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.7, 13. he who hath the fountaine of all light and comfort may be the better able to want the ſtreames; thus we have done with the firſt part of the Text, <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſickneſſe and death, we now come to the ſecond part, concerning <hi>Joaſh</hi> his viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of him, and lamenting over him. Here we have a King viſiting a Prophet; a great King, a meane Prophet; a wicked King, a religious Prophet; and we have the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt juſtifying and commending this action; from whence we may obſerve:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> That no perſon is too great to viſit a faithfull Miniſter of God in his ſickneſſe; The Pſalmiſt tels us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. that God will make the bed of a gracious and mercifull man: Now if the glorious God thinkes it not too much to be a good mans bed-maker, the higheſt of men ſhould not thinke it too much to viſit a good man. Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is a duty which Chriſt requires to be performed to all his members, and therefore ought not to be neglected towards his Meſſengers; Is any man too great to do what God commands? Though there is no reaſon why Gods will ſhould ſtoop to ours: yet there is all reaſon why our wills ſhould ſtoop to Gods; he is our Creator, we his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; he our Lord, we his Servants; he our King, we his Subjects. Now that viſiting the ſick is a duty enjoyned by Chriſt, and incumbent upon us, is cleare from that Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.42. Men uſually find fault where there is none,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117061:14"/>but there is ever a fault where Chriſt finds one.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The faithfull Meſſengers of Chriſt are no deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable perſons, low they are indeed in the opinions of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men, but the holy God hath high thoughts of them; they are his Embaſſadours, his Stewards, his Treaſurers, his Friends, yea, he cals them co-workers with himſelf; to them hath Chriſt committed the power of the keyes; they are called guides, rulers, the lights of the world, ſaviours? Why did <hi>Joaſh</hi> viſit <hi>Eliſha?</hi> He lookt upon him as one who had been an inſtrument once and againe to ſave them out of the hands of the <hi>Syrians;</hi> Miniſters are Inſtruments appointed by God to ſave, not the bodies only, but the ſoules of people out of the hands, not of fleſh and bloud, but of principalities, and powers, and ſpirituall wickedneſſes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Much advantage may be gotten by viſiting Gods faithfull Miniſters in the time of their ſickneſſe; as they have taught us by their Doctrine and example to do what God commands, ſo they may teach us to beare what God inflicts, as to live well, ſo to dye well: We may get more from them when they are upon their death-beds, than we could get from them when they were in the Pulpit; as the words of dying men come from the heart, ſo they go to the heart; we may remember their dying ſpeeches, though we have been ready to forget what formerly hath been ſpoken; we may be inſtructed by their counſels, warmed by their prayers, quickned by their exhortations, freed from the feares of death by ſeeing their boldneſſe, and courage, and learne faith, and patience from their practice. King <hi>Joaſh</hi> loſt nothing by viſiting the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> as you may read <hi>ver.</hi> 15, 16. and <hi>Eliſha</hi> loſt nothing by attending upon <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs</hi> removall from earth to heaven, as you may read 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.10. A Prince may be a great gainer by vifiting of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is a very great and ſoule-ruining ſin for any man, let him be never ſo great, in caſe he hath liberty and opportunity not to viſit the members of Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cannot waſh themſelves from guilt who neglect (wanting neither time, nor ſtrength, nor health) to viſit his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117061:14"/>Miniſters; What think we, was Chriſt in jeſt or in earneſt when he ſpake thoſe words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41, 42, 43.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Chriſt takes what is done unto his Meſſengers as done unto himſelfe, <hi>He that receiveth you</hi> (ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) <hi>receiveth me;</hi> were it poſſible for the Lord Jeſus to be ſick, we would profeſſe our willingneſſe to viſit him in ſuch an afflicted condition, and would exclaime againſt them as moſt notorious wretches, and unworthy to live, who ſhould not take a ſtep or two to wait upon Chriſt. Now read <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.40. was no man too great to attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt perſonall in the day of his diſtreſſe, neither is any too great to viſit Chriſt myſticall.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, We may do much good to the meſſengers of Chriſt by viſiting of them in their diſtreſſe; as we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive good from them, ſo they may receive good from us. <hi>Oneſimus</hi> was no ſmall comfort and ſupport to <hi>Paul,</hi> when he was in trouble. <hi>Junius</hi> reaped much ſpirituall advantage from the diſcourſe of a plaine country man; thus inferiour members of the body may be ſerviceable to the ſuperiour. Uſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This may reprove thoſe, who as they never cared for any converſe with godly Miniſters in their health, but always kept at a diſtance from them, ſo they care not for comming neare them in their ſickneſſe, not for feare of any bodily infection, but for want of ſincere and ſpirituall affection; let ſuch men know, they who love not the ſervants of Chriſt are without love to Chriſt himſelfe, and Chriſt will one day flight thoſe who have ſlighted him in his ſervants. It is to be feared, that they never got any good by the Miniſters of God vvho are diſreſpectfull unto them; novv a ſad doome hangs over the heads of all barren Chriſtians, vvho have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the choice mercy of a painfull and faithfull Miniſtry; they are neere unto curſing, and may expect to heare that ſentence, <hi>Cut them down, why cumber they the ground?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, This may reprove thoſe, vvho though they are not altogether ſo profane as to neglect the giving of a viſit to Gods meſſengers lying upon their ſick-beds, yet come to ſee them, not out of obedience to Gods command, nor
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117061:15"/>out of love to their perſons or office, nor out of any affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they beare to their doctrine, nor out of any deſire they have to comfort them, or to receive counſell or comfort from them, but meerly out of cuſtome, or in complement, or to ſtop the mouths of ſome who would cry ſhame upon thoſe who ſhould neglect ſo neceſſary, ſo charitable an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us be humbled for the neglect of this duty; ſhould God be extreame to marke our failings in this one particular, what would become of us? <hi>Jobs</hi> friends tooke a long and a tedious journey to ſee him when they heard how the hand of God was upon him, but how often are we backward to take a journey of two or three houres riding, nay, to ſtep a bows-ſhoot out of doores to viſit an afflicted member of Chriſt, to communicate with him in his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, to comfort him in his griefes, to refreſh and revive him with our preſence, and ſpiritual and pertinent diſcourſe? How ſhould we ſhame our ſelves for this our want of love to the command of Chriſt to the members of Chriſt, yea, to Chriſt himſelfe? Well, let us cry <hi>peccavi,</hi> beg our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and looke upon it as a matter of duty, to viſit thoſe with our perſonall preſence, whom Chriſt will vouchſafe to viſit with his gracious preſence. The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all thoſe from being truly religious, who make no conſcience of the performance of this worke of love, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27. Are there any of Gods friends and our acquaintance, any of Gods Meſſengers and our Paſtors, any of Chriſts Members and our Brethren, caſt upon the bed of ſickneſſe? Let us imitate Chriſt, who when he heard <hi>Lazarus</hi> was ſick, went down to ſee him. Let not this example of <hi>Joaſh</hi> riſe up in judgement againſt us and condemne us; would we not have others to expreſſe ſuch a kindneſſe to us? Let us not deny that to others which we expect from others, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. But let us not give complementall viſits only, the ſin of the times we live in; but ſo diſcharge what God cals for in this buſineſſe, that God may have Glory, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon viſited comfort, and we our ſelves benefit and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:117061:15"/>
            <p> Firſt, Viſit, whether Paſtor, or Neighbour, out of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Gods command; let Gods command, not baſe, and by reſpects, carry thee on to this worke; no action of ours, though enjoyned by God, will be accepted of, unleſſe it be done out of obedience to that God who enjoynes it, <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Do this that Chriſt cals for out of love to Chriſt, then will Chriſt take it as done unto himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Do this duty with an honeſt heart, and ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the Prophet <hi>David</hi> tels us of ſome that came to ſee him in his ſickneſſe, but not out of any cordiall affection they did beare unto him, but for baſe ends, to ſee whether there were any hopes that he would dye, or to gather ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or other from him that might prejudice him in his credit and eſteeme, and render him odious.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Since God muſt make every office performed unto others comfortable unto them, and profitable unto us, let us, upon ſuch occaſions, and at ſuch times, lift up a ſecret prayer unto God, that ſuch a meeting or viſitation might be bleſſed with the fruits of mutuall joy, quickning, and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Having diſpatched this Doctrine, we now come to the effects that <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh</hi> his viſiting of our Prophet did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, and they are two: Firſt, He wept over his face. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, He gave him honourable titles. 1. He caſs him his Father. 2. He ſtiles him the Chariot of Iſrael, and the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thereof; from his weeping over the Prophet now ready to expire, we may obſerve,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> That the death of godly and painful Miniſters is matter of great lamentation; all forts of people, good and bad, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and unrighteous, have cauſe to mourne, and bitterly to bewaile the death of ſuch Miniſters who have been pious and faithfull.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Church in generall, the whole company of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, who know and heare of it, have cauſe to mourne; Miniſters are given to the Church for her gaine, and cannot be taken away without her loſſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12. They are not only members of her body, but ſuch members which are very uſefull and neceſſary; they are called the lights, guides,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117061:16"/>watchmen of the Church; yea, they are called her rulers; let a man loſe any one member it would trouble him, but the more uſefull any member is, the greater will be his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The wicked have cauſe to mourne when God takes away his faithfull Miniſters; <hi>Joaſh</hi> was of this mind, otherwiſe he would not have done what he did; good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon there is why graceleſs men ſhould lay to heart the death of gracious Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is never more angry with wicked men, than when he removes his Meſſengers from them; true, bad men are never more merry than when good Miniſters are laid in the duſt, but they have more cauſe to ſigh than to ſing, to cry than to laugh. If to be let alone in ſin without check or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe be a judgement, then certainly it is a judgement to wicked men when godly Miniſters are taken away, who by their reproofes and counſels did what they could to keep them from ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They have loſt one who did both earneſtly deſire, and conſtantly endeavour their ſpirituall and eternall good, and therefore they have cauſe to mourne; if the loſſe of a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily friend be matter of griefe, what matter of griefe is the loſs of a ſoule friend?</p>
            <p n="3">3. They have loſt one that ſtood in the gap to keep off judgements from breaking in upon them: had it not been for the prayers and teares of their faithfull Paſtor, divine vengeance might have ceaſed upon them long before now; how many times hath God been ready to draw his ſword to cut them off, to lay his axe to the root of them, and to chop them down, when their watchfull and compaſſionate over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer hath interceded for them, and held Gods hands from deſtroying them. <hi>Jeremies</hi> prayers for the Jews did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with God for a ſeaſon to ſpare them, and when God was fully determined to ruine them, he bids <hi>Jeremy</hi> not to pray for them, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.23. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.30, 31. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The godly where ſuch a Miniſter did live have cauſe to mourne when he is taken away; for,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:117061:16"/> 1. As God is angry with the wicked, ſo he is angry with his own people when he deprives them of their Paſtor; it is promiſed as a ſingular teſtimony of Gods love to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to let them have the liberty of ſeeing the faces, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the labours of their Teachers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They have loſt one who was watchfull over them, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to prevent their falling into ſin, and ready to raiſe them up with all poſſible ſpeed when fallen.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some of them have loſt a ſpirituall father, and ought not the child to lament the loſſe of his father? Beſides, all of them have loſt a diligent inſtructer.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They have loſt one who through Gods bleſſing hath kept them out of many a ſnare, carried on the work of grace in their hearts, awakened their drouzy ſoules, quickened their dead hearts, ſtrengthened their feeble hands and knees, revived their almoſt expiring graces, reduced them when they have been wandring, encouraged them in the waies of God when they met with ſtrong oppoſition, comforted them when they have been ſad, anſwered their doubts, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered their feares, and filled them with joy and peace through beleeving, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They have loſt one who was acquainted with their condition, knew in ſome meaſure the ſtate of their ſoules, and ſo was the better able to ſpeake ſeaſonably to them, and to their neceſſities. A ſtranger may preach wholſome truths to a people, but he knows not ſo well to apply his doctrine to them as their own Paſtor. Another may give a child meat to eate, but he cannot tell what that food is which is moſt convenient for it ſo well as the mother; that Phyſitian who hath been longeſt acquainted with our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies knows what Phyſick is moſt proper for us; thus you ſee all ſorts have cauſe to lament the fall of a faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; the reaſons are theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, God commands us to mourne when he afflicts us with the loſſe of godly and painefull Miniſters; when God was pleaſed to take away <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> none of the beſt Prieſts, and ſuch who died in their ſin, yet even then did God call upon the people to bewaile the burning which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117061:17"/>he had made, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Muſt the death of wicked ones be lamented? then certainly we muſt lament the death of the righteous. Muſt not <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> go to their graves without teares? What teares ſhould we poure out when a <hi>Samuel,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> or a <hi>Stephen</hi> go to their graves?</p>
            <p>Secondly, It hath been the practice of the godly bitterly to bewaile the loſſe of pious and faithfull Miniſters; what is written in this particular is written for our learning; we muſt be followers of thoſe who are good, ſo far as they are followers of that which is good, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.1. <hi>Micah</hi> 7.1. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.37, 38. it went to their very hearts to thinke that they ſhould loſe one who had been ſuch a notable inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to promote Gods glory and his Churches good. <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> writing of the life of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> reports thus much of him, <hi>Quod flebat amariſſimè quotieſcunque fortè annuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum illi fuerat de cujuſcunque ſancti obitu Sacerdotis;</hi> that he wept moſt bitterly whenever any one told him of the death of any godly Miniſter. It is alſo reported of <hi>Philo,</hi> that when he heard where he came of the death of any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, man he would weep very bitterly, becauſe the Town and the Church had no ſmall prejudice by ſuch a loſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Such as have had no grace have lamented the death of the Prophets and Meſſengers of God; we have <hi>Joaſh</hi> for an example, who will riſe up in judgment againſt, and condemne thoſe who can let godly Miniſters go to their graves without ſighs in their hearts, or teares in their eyes; when the old Prophet, who ſeduced the Prophet ſent to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> ſaw that he was ſlaine by the Lion, he brought his carkaſſe into the City, laid it in his own grave, and they mourned over him with the Text, ſaying, <hi>Alas my brother,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.30.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God complaines of thoſe who neglected to lay to heart the death of the righteous, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1. God never finds fault where there is none, were it not a duty to lament the loſſe of Gods ſervants none ſhould have met with a check for the neglect of it.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Peoples ſins are the cauſe of Gods taking away their faithfull Paſtors; the unthankfulneſſe and unfruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117061:17"/>of heares provoke God to remove their preachers, and ought we not to lay to heart thoſe ſins which deprive us of very choice mercies?</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The death of Gods faithfull Miniſters is the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of ſome approaching judgement: what but dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe can be expected when the Sun is ſet? Have we not cauſe to feare an inundation of waters when the banks that kept them from overflowing are cut down? If the pillars of a houſe be taken away, can the houſe ſtand? If the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men be killed, the City is in danger to be ſurprized, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1. Hiſtory tels us, that ſo ſoon as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> was dead and gone, the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> broke into <hi>Hippo,</hi> the City where he lived, and ſpoyled it. The <hi>Smakaldicke</hi> war be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in <hi>Germany</hi> not long after <hi>Luther</hi> was laid in the grave. <hi>Spinola</hi> took <hi>Heilderberg</hi> not long after God had taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that precious ſervant of his <hi>Pareus.</hi> You ſee then there is no ſmall cauſe of mourning, when God takes away his faithfull Meſſengers and Miniſters. Uſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This ſerves to reprove thoſe who are not affected with the loſſe of Gods faithfull Miniſters, thoſe righteous men periſh, and how few lay it to heart? They go to their long home, but where are the mourners about the ſtreets? God hath been pleaſed of late to put out many ſhining and burning lights, as Dr <hi>Hill,</hi> Mr <hi>Whitaker,</hi> Mr <hi>Gataker,</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Bolton,</hi> and many others, men famous in their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, uſefull and precious, men of whom the world was not worthy; we heare of the fall of thoſe Cedars, but trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not, of the removall of thoſe pillars, but are not afraid; we regard the loſſe of thoſe bleſſed inſtruments no more than the loſſe of a horſe or hog; no more ſay I? nay, not ſo much; <hi>Gadaren</hi>-like, we can better part with the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Chriſt than with our ſwine, ſpend more ſighs and complaints upon the deaths of brute creatures, than upon the deaths of Gods Embaſſadours, and our inſtructors. Oh the wonderfull ſtupidity and hardneſs of heart that are too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in all places; God was very angry with the Jews be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they regarded not the operation of his hands, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.12. Inſenſibility under preſent judgements makes way for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117061:18"/>How can we think God ſhould betruſt us any more with his Meſsengers and Miniſters, when we can part with them without any conſiderable griefe and ſorrow? Too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny care not what become either of State, or Church, or their own precious ſoules, ſo they may enjoy their eſtates, their liberties, their carnall profits and pleaſures; let God take away one pious Miniſter after another, or godly man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, they are ready to ſay as the Phariſees to <hi>Judas, What is that to us?</hi> What is this to you? Do you thinke it is nothing to you that godly Miniſters are taken away? Is it nothing to you that God is angry? Is it nothing to you that you lye naked to the indignation of the Almighty? Is it nothing to you that your ſoules are in danger to miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Is it nothing to you that you are expoſed to temptations, ſnares, and ſin, and that you have loſt one that was wont to watch over you, pitty and pray for you? Is it nothing to you that the wall or fence is taken away that kept the little Foxes and Wolves from breaking in upon you to devoure your precious foules? Is it nothing to you that you have loſt one that ſtood in the gap to keep off Gods wrath and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance from falling upon you that live in theſe times wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in knowledge abounds? read you the Scriptures; have you any acquaintance with the mind and will of God? And is it nothing to you <hi>Eliſhas, Stevens, Samuels, Pauls</hi> are taken away? You will find it ſomething one day.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It ſerves to reproove thoſe who are ſo far from laying to heart the death of Gods faithfull Miniſters, that they rather are glad of it, and rejoyce in it, ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, ſome openly; the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes of ſome who came to viſit him in his ſickneſs, and ſeemed to be troubled at it in outward appearance, but were glad at the very heart that there was ſome likelihood of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ath; ſome there are who would not have the world think them ſo prophane as to rejoyce at the fall of precious and godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, who are ſecretly glad of it, and ſay with their hearts, though not with their tongues, as they did, Aha, Aha, ſo would we have it; but ſhall not God find ſuch out? Is not he who ſearcheth the heart, and trieth the reines privy to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117061:18"/>this their diabolicall joy? How can, how dare ſuch call God father, or thinke themſelves Gods children, who are glad to behold the funerals of their brethren? Naturall bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren may rejoyce at the death one of another, hoping to reape ſome diſadvantage thereby: But certainly ſpirituall brethren, who cannot be rent one from another without diſadvantage to the ſurvivers, will be otherwiſe affected; they are falſe brethren, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, and curſed hypocrites, who make the death of any godly Miniſter the matter of their rejoycing. Againe, others there are who proclaime their ſin as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and ſtick not to profeſſe that they are glad at the very heart that ſuch and ſuch godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are taken away, like thoſe ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.10. who made merry, and ſent gifts one to another when the two witneſſes were ſlaine. Now they thinke they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their ſins more freely, and ſhall not meet with ſuch ſharp reproofes for them, that their conſciences will not trouble them ſo much as they were wont to do; but can any ſolid ground of joy be drawn from hence? It is all one as if a man ſhould rejoyce that ſuch a Phyſitian is dead, who whilſt he lived did what he could to keep him from feeding upon ſuch meats as would haſten death. It is as if a man ſhould rejoyce that he is taken away who did what he could to preſerve him from deſtroying himſelfe. I tell thee whoever thou art who pleaſeſt thy ſelfe with the loſſe of Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters thou haſt no cauſe to rejoyce at this; their deaths will be ſo far from bettering thy condition, that thy condition is likely to be worſe for their deaths. Satan will now take fuller poſſeſſion of thee, thy ſins will now have more power over thee, thy iniquities will the ſooner be ripe, and thou wilt the ſooner be cut down; and is this any matter of joy? Gods hands were ever and anon ready to deſtroy thee whileſt they lived, their prayers and teares kept his ſword from being ſheathed in thee: and doſt thou think thou art ever awhit the ſafer from danger and ruine? Is the houſe and thoſe who are in it ever a jot the ſafer becauſe the pillars that kept it up are removed? Thy conſcience when thou ſateſt under a godly Miniſtry did ever and anon check
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117061:19"/>thee, grant it now proves ſpeechleſſe and ſaies nothing; can there be a more dreadfull judgement than a ſilent and dumb conſcience? Before there was ſome ſtrugling in thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt temptations to ſin, and now thou canſt commit ſin without any reluctancy, with all greedineſſe, this is matter of lamentation, not of joy: Are Gods Miniſters gone? They are gone to give an account how thou haſt carried thy ſelfe towards God and them, and God upon their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint may haſten the execution of his judgements upon thee and thine; thou haſt more cauſe to tremble at their deaths than to hug thy ſelfe, to ſigh than to ſing. Do not dreame that God hath taken them away to ſhew thee any kindneſſe, that they are removed out of favour to thee, who haſt been a bitter enemy, as to them, ſo unto God. No, no, it is in wrath, not in mercy towards thee that God hath ſent for them home; their lives were not more burdenſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, than their deaths will prove prejudiciall and bane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; now will the devill triumph more over thee, and carry thee captive at his will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us mourne when God takes away any of his faithfull Meſſengers from us; Let not God complaine of us as he did of thoſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1. Let not <hi>Joaſh</hi> riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt us and condemne us; make we a difference between an <hi>Eliſha</hi> and a <hi>Jehojachin, Jer.</hi> 22 18. Do we love the Lord? let us mourne that one who was zealous for his glory is gone from amongſt us; do we love Chriſt? let us mourne that one of the friends of the Bridegroome is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away; do we love the Church? let us mourne that ſhe is deprived of one of her choice members; do we love the State? let us mourne that one of her pillars are removed; do we love the truth? let us mourne that one who was vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant for it is departed; do we love our ſoules? let us mourne that one who was carefull for them, watchfull over them, mercifull to them, is gone; gone, gone, never to be ſeen in this place, nor in any of your houſes or families againe; do we love our neighbours and brethren? let us mourne that they as well as we have loſt at one clap a faithfull friend, a faithfull counſellour, a faithfull inſtructer, a faithfull repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117061:19"/>a faithfull comforter, in a word, a faithfull Preacher; Let every one of us mourne together, and yet mourne apart; let the wife mourn that ſhe hath loſt ſo pious a yoke-fellow; let his children mourn that they have loſt ſo carefull a father; let the ſervants mourn that they have loſt ſo religious a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; let the people mourne that they have loſt ſo painfull a Paſtor; and let us Miniſters mourne that we have loſt ſuch a fellow-labourer, one that did joyne with us, and help us to oppoſe thoſe grand enemies, Sin, Satan, and the World. True it is, none have cauſe to mourne, in reference to his preſent condition, but rather to rejoyce; he hath fought a good fight, finiſhed his courſe, and kept the faith, and now is wearing that crown of righteouſneſs which hath been prepared for him. Could he ſpeake unto us, he would ſay as Chriſt to the women who be wailed and lamented him, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.28. Weepe not for me, but weepe for your ſelves. Let us ſearch our hearts and lives, and find out the cauſes of this our loſſe, why God hath given us ſuch a cup of gall and wormwood for to drinke: And is there not a cauſe? Yes certainly. Our unthankfulneſſe, our unfruitfulneſſe, our pride, our worldlineſs, our deadneſs, our coldneſs, our luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs, our hypocriſie, our contempt and undervaluing of ſuch a bleſſing have provoked God to deprive us of him. The loſſe of our firſt love hath made God to ſcourge us with this loſs, a loſs with a witneſs, a loſs to many at once, a loſs to the State, a loſs to the Church, a loſs to the Country, a loſs to his Pariſh, a loſs to his Neighbours, a loſs to his Yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow, a loſs to his Children, a loſs to his Brethren, we have loſt we know not what; this loſs may be more felt hereafter than it is for the preſent. I wiſh you may never have cauſe to ſay, where is the ſpirit of <hi>Elijah?</hi> Where is he now whoſe zeale was wont to inflame our hearts, whoſe forwardneſs for God was wont to put us forward, whoſe teares were wont to ſet us on mourning, whoſe ſpirituall fervour was wont to heate and warme us, whoſe elevated heart in the waies of God hath helped to lift up our hearts in Gods waies, the prevalency of whoſe prayers we were wont to feele in the encreaſing and quickning of our graces,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117061:20"/>whoſe powerfull Sermons were wont to leave moſt ſweet and refreſhing influences upon our ſoules? Where is he? Where is he? God grant that the ſpirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> may be doubled upon his ſucceſſour, that you may not pine and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh away in ſuch ſad complaints. I make no queſtion, were it in the power of prayers and teares, of faſting and mourning to fetch him back againe, you would not be long without him. But now it is too late; thankfulneſs, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and a cloſe walking with God might have kept him ſtill amongſt you, who cannot be recalled by any teares or ſupplications. Thus having finiſhed the firſt thing that <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſh</hi> did after he came to ſee <hi>Eliſha,</hi> we come now to ſpeake of the ſecond effect or fruit of his viſitation, expreſsed in the honourable titles which he gave unto him; Firſt, he cals him his Father; from whence we may obſerve:</p>
            <p>That honour and reſpect ought to be ſhewed from all ſorts of men to the faithfull Meſsengers and Miniſters of God. <hi>Joaſh</hi> did no more than his duty; the ſpirit of God would not have left it upon record for his commendation had it not been a thing that God liked and approved. All Sexes, whether men or women, all relations, whether Prince or people, husband or wife, or all degrees, whether high or low, rich or poore, all conditions, whether good or bad, righteous, or unrighteous, learned or unlearned, are bound to honour and reſpect the Meſsengers and Miniſters of Chriſt; there is an inward honour belongs unto them, we are highly to eſteeme of them, to love them; there is an outward honour belongs to them, we are to honour them in our words, by ſpeaking well of them, and reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to them, we are to honour them in our geſtures and carriages towards them; the <hi>Babylonians</hi> were charged with this fault, that they reſpected not the perſons of the Prieſts, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.57. It ſeemes then nothing was more common and ordinary than to ſhew reſpect and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Prophets of God, 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 5.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God honours them, and therefore men ſhould not neglect to honour them; it is ground enough for us to love
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117061:20"/>a man becauſe God loves him, and to reſpect men becauſe God reſpects them; Chriſt would have us to be mercifull that we might be like unto our heavenly Father who is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. So we muſt honour thoſe whom God ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, that we might expreſſe our conformity unto God; <hi>What ſhall be done unto the man whom the King will honour?</hi> ſaith <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> to <hi>Haman, Eſt.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Haman</hi> thought no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour too great for, and none too great to honour ſuch a man; what ſhall then be done unto the men whom the King of Kings will honour? Surely, mortall men ſhould not thinke much to honour thoſe whom the immortall God thinkes not much to honour. Now there is no faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter whom God doth not, hath not, will not highly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. they honour God, and God will honour them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Their Office is an honourable office, their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling an honourable calling, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. to be a Steward to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man is a place of honour; Yearely Stewards, if I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake not, are Eſquires by their places, as Knights eldeſt Sons are by their birth. To be Lord High Steward to a Prince is a place of greater honour: Now all Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are Stewards to that God who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. Againe, the Office of an Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, who repreſents the perſon of the King, is a place of great honour: Miniſters are Gods Embaſſadours, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiate for God, and they are employed to treat about a peace between God and man, about a marriage between Chriſt and the ſoules of people, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. Again, they are ſaid to be co-workers, and fellow labourers with God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the ſalvation of ſinners, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 9.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Good men have been ready and carefull to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Meſsengers and Miniſters of God; ſuch who have ſlighted them before their Converſion have much reſpect and reverence unto them after converſion. Thoſe, who mockt at <hi>Peter</hi> and the Apoſtles when they were in the ſtate of nature, did very much honour them after they were wrought upon by <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>Cornelius</hi> a good man was ready to go beyond his bounds in ſhewing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117061:21"/>honour to <hi>Peter,</hi> he was ready to give him too much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect rather than too little. <hi>Acts.</hi> 10.25. How much favour and kindneſs did the <hi>Shunamite</hi> and her husband manifeſt to the Prophet <hi>Eliſha?</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.8. the <hi>Galatians</hi> eſteemed <hi>Paul</hi> as an Angel of God, and received him as Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.14.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Wicked men have been ready to reverence and to reſpect the faithfull Meſſengers and Miniſters of God; How highly did <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> honour the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel? Chap.</hi> 2.46, 47. <hi>Darius</hi> alſo did not a little reſpect and prize him. <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> ſhewed much reverence to the Prophet <hi>Eliſha; Herod</hi> reverenced <hi>John Baptiſt, Mar.</hi> 6.20. and the <hi>Barbarians</hi> beſtowed upon <hi>Paul</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany many honours; we ſee then that both by the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God and man there is an honour due from all ſorts of people to Gods faithfull Meſsengers and Miniſters. Uſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It ſerves to reprove thoſe who make it their work and trade to revile and reproach the faithfull Meſsengers and Miniſters of God, looke upon them with ſcorne and contempt, count them as the off-ſcouring of all things, and rakehell it ſelfe for baſe termes and names to caſt upon them; perſons truly religious in former times were known by their love to, and eſteeme of godly and conſciencious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: but now ſcorne and contempt of godly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciencious Miniſters is the practice of thoſe who would be thought, and ſtile themſelves to be the Saints and religious ones; what the Apoſtle ſpake concerning that wiſdome which was attended with envy, and ſtrife, that it was earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſenſuall, and devilliſh, ſo we may ſay of that Religion which puts men upon rayling againſt, and reproving the Meſsengers and ſervants of the Lord, that it is earthly, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall, and devilliſh; a Religion of the devills ſetting up, and not of Gods appointing. <hi>Michael</hi> diſputing with the devill about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> dared not to bring a rayling accuſation againſt him; you know men full of fierceneſs and bitterneſs againſt dignities, whether in State or Church, whatever formes they may have are called clouds without water, raging waves of the ſea, foaming out their own
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117061:21"/>ſhame, wandring ſtars, to whom is reſerved the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of darkneſſe for ever. Never were Gods Embaſſadors more ſlighted and deſpiſed than in theſe daies, but let ſuch deſpiſers know, that God takes the ſcornes and contempts caſt upon them as caſt upon himſelfe; and though he is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and long-ſuffering, yet will find a time to be avenged of all ſuch <hi>Rabſhekahs, Luk.</hi> 10.16. No ſin haſtens the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Gods judgements upon a State ſooner than this ſin, 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 36.16. we read of ſome who never proſpered after they ſet themſelves to oppoſe Gods Meſſengers and Miniſters, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.12. <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.25. <hi>Chap.</hi> 25.16. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.18.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Is there an honour due from all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to Gods faithfull Meſſengers and Miniſters? let us not rob Gods Meſſengers and Miniſters of that honour which is their due; they are worthy of double honour ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, the honour of reverence, and the honour of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, let us not be ſo unworthy as to deny it them; in honouring of them we honour God, as in deſpiſing of them we deſpiſe God; though Iſrael play the harlot, yet let not <hi>Judah</hi> offend; though the vile ones of the world ſlight and ſcorne faithfull Preachers and Paſtors, yet let not thoſe who profeſſe the Goſpell tread in their ſteps, but walke according to what the Goſpell injoynes in this particular, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.11. by ſlighting of us you hurt your ſelves more than you wrong us; our ſalvation is furthered, not hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by your ſcornes, theſe light afflictions worke for us a far more exceeding and eternall weight of glory, but your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is much hindered by ſlighting and contemning of us, that doctrine and meſſage will be the leſſe regarded by you which we bring from our Lord &amp; Maſter to you: call we up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you to render us that honour which is our due, and your duty in reference to our ſelves, only or for our own comfort and encouragement? No certainly, but for your benefit and advantage alſo; you will get but little good by your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters labours, ſo long as you have low and deſpicable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of their perſons; take heed therefore of this ſin of the times, ſlight not thoſe whom God commands you to honour, hate not thoſe whom God would have you love. Be not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117061:22"/>worſe than <hi>Joaſh.</hi> If any ſhall ſay, <hi>Joaſh</hi> had good reaſon to obſerve and honour <hi>Eliſha,</hi> for he was a Prophet; were our Miniſters Prophets and able to do as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did, we were to blame ſhould we not expreſſe all warrantable reverence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: As for thoſe who make this objection, let them heare what our Saviour ſpake, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.11.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Let me ſpeake a word or two to you my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and my ſelfe; Let us do nothing that may deprive us of that honour which belongs unto us; ſo let us walke, ſo humbly, ſo inoffenſively, ſo holily, ſo exemplarily in every good word and worke, that we may keep up the tottering honour both of our Office and Perſons; Let us make it our buſineſſe to honour God, by laying out our ſelves to encreaſe his Kingdome by a faithfull performance of thoſe duties which God calls for at our hands in our places, by being patterns of faith and patience, meekneſſe and ſelfe deniall, contempt of the world, and heavenly mindedneſſe, and God will honour us, good men will honour us, yea God can make our worſt enemies to honour us. We now come to the laſt doctrine which may be gathered from the ſecond ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of honour which this King gave unto <hi>Eliſha,</hi> he calls him the Chariot of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof; he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that all Iſrael were as much (if not more) beholden to the Prophet for their defence and ſafety as to their Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots and horſemen; from hence we may obſerve thus much:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>
               </label> That Gods faithfull Miniſters are a great defence to the nation and people where they live; what <hi>Joaſh</hi> ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Eliſha,</hi> the ſame did <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſpeak concerning <hi>Elijah,</hi> ſo that we have not this teſtimony only from the mouth or a wicked Prince, but alſo from the mouth of a holy Prophet. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.12. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.13, 17. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.9, 10. <hi>Chap.</hi> 31.21. Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe they make it their worke to ſuppreſſe and beat down ſin which makes a nation naked and weake, and expoſeth it to all manner of judgements. God is the defence of every nation, whileſt he is with a people, they need not feare, but ſin will drive God away, it will deprive a people of their defence, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.9. Now Miniſters by preaching againſt, and oppoſing of ſin take a courſe to keep God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtill amongſt a people.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:117061:22"/>
            <p> Secondly. The prayers of Gods faithfull Miniſters are very prevalent with God, both for the continuance of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and the keeping off of judgments. <hi>Moſes</hi> his prayer did as much good as <hi>Joſhuahs</hi> ſword when the people of Iſrael encountred with <hi>Amaleck.</hi> The houſe of <hi>Abimelech</hi> was in great danger of ruine, but upon <hi>Abrahams</hi> prayer God ſpared it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.7. How often was God ready to cut off the people of Iſrael, but <hi>Moſes</hi> by his earneſt cries and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications ſtayed Gods hand. If <hi>Jeremy</hi> will pray for the people of the Jews, Gods knows not how to deny his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and therefore when God was reſolved to deſtroy them, he commands <hi>Jeremy</hi> to pray no more for them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.10.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe Gods faithfull Miniſters do what they can to advance the true Religion, to ſet up the ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice of God in the places where they live; their ſtudy is to draw people unto Chriſt, and to promote and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the kingdome of the Lord Jeſus. Now God hath been very favourable to a people and nation where his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice hath been ſet up and maintained, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.17. How did they ſtrengthen the kingdome of <hi>Judah</hi> by offering ſacrifices to the Lord according to the manner God had preſcribed? See alſo, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God many times for his Miniſters ſake is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſpare a nation, and will not deſtroy it till he hath ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured them; the old world fared the better for <hi>Noah</hi> that preacher of righteouſnes; had he been houſed ſooner, they might have been ruined ſooner. The Angel told <hi>Lot</hi> that he could nothing againſt <hi>Sodom</hi> till he was gone out of it, and therefore he bids him make haſte. That fearefull rout which the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> gave <hi>Saul,</hi> when he and his Sons were ſlaine, fell not upon him till after <hi>Samuels</hi> death. Uſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let God and the world judge whether they are a Nations friends, who are bitter enemies to the Miniſters of God, who ſay of them as thoſe did, <hi>Come, let us cut them off from being in the nation, that their name may be had no more in remembrance;</hi> were the Philiſtines the Iſraelites friends when they took away all their military weapons, and would not allow them either ſwords or ſpeares to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117061:23"/>themſelves: no better friends are they to a State who endeavour to deprive it of Gods faithfull Meſſengers, who are no leſſe neceſſary for the defence and ſafety of a State than Chariots and horſemen; if ſuch be lovers of Chriſt or Chriſtians, I do not know who may be accounted ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Then the way to ſecure a nation againſt all adverſe power, and to make it happy and glorious, is to plant, ſet up, and maintaine a godly and painfull Miniſtry in every place, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.17. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was of this mind, and therefore he took care that the Levites might be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged in their worke, and ſurely they are far from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and zeale of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> who do what they can to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Meſsengers of the Lord in the worke of the Miniſtry, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.4.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Have nothing to do with thoſe men whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne it is to pull down the publike Miniſtry, to burne up thoſe Chariots, to unhorſe thoſe horſemen, to demoliſh thoſe bulwarkes, and to break down thoſe fences, that ſo foxes, and wolves, and ravenous beaſts may breake in upon us; ſay not a confederacy to whom this people ſhall ſay a confederacy, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.12. but rather ſay as good <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.6. Oh my ſoule come not thou into their ſecret, unto their Aſsembly mine honour be not thou united.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Have we not then great cauſe to mourne and be humbled, when God takes away thoſe Chariots and horſemen, his faithfull Meſsengers and Miniſters, from our heads? Would not England be in a ſad condition, were ſhe deprived of her weapons of defence, when the Nations round about would be glad if they were able to make an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode upon us; when a people loſe their Miniſters, when thoſe chariots and horſemen are removed, the place and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion where they once lived lie more naked and open to all manner of judgements. I cannot blame you that I ſee ſo many ſad faces, ſome weeping eyes amongſt you. <hi>Rachel</hi> wept becauſe ſhe had loſt her children, and you have cauſe to weep becauſe you have loſt a ſpirituall father; and we have all cauſe to mourne if we conſider what a one he was whom we have loſt: He was a painfull Preacher, laid out
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117061:23"/>himſelfe in the Lords vineyard, and was carefull to fulfill the Miniſtry which he had received in the Lord. He was no leſſe faithfull than painfull, he was one who would not keep back any of Gods counſels, but was ready to reveale unto his people the whole truth, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. He ſtudied to divide the word of truth aright, and to give every one that portion which did of right belong unto him: as he would tell the righteous it ſhould be well with them, ſo he would tell the wicked it ſhould be ill with them. He was one who would not daube with untempered morter, neither was he afraid to reprove the greateſt of ſinners to their faces, he wrought in the worke of the Miniſtry very willingly, and not out of conſtraint; it was not filthy lucre, nor popular applauſe, nor any ſuch corrupt end that drew him forth to preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell love to Chriſt, an earneſt deſire to encreaſe his kingdom, pitty and compaſſion towards poore ſoules, a violent thirſt after their ſalvation, and a burning zeale for the honour and glory of God were the motives that put him upon this worke, nothing grieved him more than when God denied him the liberty of preaching, and he was never better than when in the Pulpit. I have heard him often ſay, that he had rather be ſick two daies of the ſix than upon the Sabbath day. In the time of this his laſt ſickneſs he would often ſay, When ſhall I be able to preach againe? And when he felt but a little reviving and ſtrength he was very glad, upon this account, becauſe he hoped ere long he ſhould declare Gods will again to his people in the publike Congregation; what was the longing of <hi>Davids</hi> ſoul, was alſo the longing of his, ſighing out thoſe words, <hi>When ſhall I come and appeare before God? Pſal.</hi> 42.2. No burden lay heavier upon his ſpirit than his preſent inability to be ſerviceable unto God in his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall Office; he was none of thoſe, who are glad of any excuſe to juſtifie their ſitting ſtill and not preaching to their Flock. He pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> no doctrine upon his people but what he would venture his own ſalvation upon, and upon his death-bed deſired his people to cleave faſt to thoſe truths which he had taught them, for he durſt pawn his ſoule upon them. He was moſt carefull of, and loving to his people; when he was called to be a Member of the Aſſembly, he was forced
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117061:24"/>to leave them, but it was <hi>cum animo revertendi,</hi> with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to returne againe unto them. He had a very great li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in <hi>London,</hi> but this could not keep him from comming back to his old place ſo ſoone as he had liberty and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. I have heard him often ſay, he would not exchange <hi>Wilby</hi> for the greateſt Living in the Land Great Livings have ſeverall times been laid down at hi feet, but he would not accept of them. When he thought he ſhould dye, he called his people together, bleſſed them in the name of the Lord, prayed earneſtly with them, and for them, and entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to keep cloſe to God, to wait upon the publike Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, not to forſake (as the manner of ſome is) the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Miniſtry, to take heed of being carried away with the errours of the wicked, and that they fell not from their ſtedfaſtneſſe. Oh let thoſe and ſuch like counſels of his be precious to you who heard them, thinke much of them, walke according to them, let theſe words of your dying Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor never be forgotten: Be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you. He was a ſucceſſefull Preacher, God went along with his Miniſtry; he did not labour in vaine, neither did he ſpend his ſtrength in vaine; he was a ſpirituall father to many children. I muſt confeſs (admiring and adoring God for the freeneſſe of his grace, and the riches of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) that the firſt breathings of ſpirituall life which ever I felt were under his Miniſtry. Others no queſtion have been no leſſe laborious in their Maſters vineyard than this bleſſed ſervant of God, but all, nay, few in theſe parts of late have been ſo fruitfull in begetting of children unto God. It may be ſaid of him as it was ſaid of <hi>Octavius,</hi> that when he came to <hi>Rome</hi> he found the walls made of common and ordinary ſtone, but left them walls of marble: When he came to <hi>Wilby</hi> he found a company of Atheiſts, but hath left a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Beleevers, he found a company of Blaſphemers, but hath left a company bleſſing and glorifying of God, he found a company of drunkards, but hath left a company of ſober men, he found a company of prophane ones, but hath let a company of holy ones, he found them enemies unto God, but hath left them Gods friends, ſo that he could ſay to
<pb facs="tcp:117061:24"/>his people as once the Apoſtle to the <hi>Romans, Chap.</hi> 6.16, 17. <hi>But God be thanked that ye were the ſervants of ſin, but ye have obeyed from the heart that forme of doctrine which was delivered unto you; Being then made free from ſin, ye became the ſervants of righteouſneſs.</hi> Now give me leave to preſs the ſubſequent words upon you his people by way of exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As you have yielded your members ſervants to unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to iniquity unto iniquity, even ſo now yeeld your members ſervants to righteouſneſſe unto holineſſe: Againe, as God uſed this bleſſed ſervant of his to be an inſtrument to encreaſe his kingdome, and to bring ſoules home unto him, ſo he made him an inſtrument to keep thoſe whom he had converted from being drawn a way with the errour of the wicked. How many Miniſters may ſay of ſome of their moſt hopefull people as <hi>Paul</hi> of the <hi>Galatians,</hi> that they are removed from thoſe truths and ordinances which they once ſeemed to embrace, that they are enemies to that Miniſtry which they once ſeemed to reſpect and honour, ſome being turned Seekers, ſome Quakers, ſome Arminians, ſome An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomians, ſome Antiſabbatarians, ſome Anabaptiſts, and what not? But God hath been pleaſed to keep his people from falling into the ſnares of ſeducing ſpirits; the foxes and the wolves have not made a prey of them they turned not their backs upon his Miniſtry, they forſooke not the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ordinances; and let it not O ye people of <hi>Wilby</hi> be ſaid, ye did run well, who did drive you back that you ſhould not obey the truth? Stand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made you free, and be not entangled with any of thoſe ſoule-ruining ſnares wherein many are caught.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, He was a zealous Preacher, full of ſpirituall heat, filled with a holy indignation againſt ſin, ſtirring and active for his God; he did not the worke of his Maſter negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but was willing to ſpend himſelfe, and to be ſpent in his Lords ſervice. Now as his life was holy, ſo his death was ſweet and comfortable. He told me, that he bleſſed God he was not afraid to dye. God did not let looſe that accuſer of the brethren upon him, but filled his heart with joy and peace unſpeakable and glorious; what cauſe, faith he, have we to triumph? God is our glory, God is our joy. Being at
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117061:25"/>one time full of paine, and in his own apprehenſion too im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient, he asked his neighbours whether they were not grieved at his impatience? who ſaying nothing, he ſpake thus unto them: Truly I am not impatient for want of inward comfort, for as I have not ſo little as to conceale it, ſo I have ſo much that I am not able fully to expreſſe it. He did ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly long to be diſſolved, that he might be with Chriſt, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten crying out, when will that houre come? It is but one knock more, and then this earthen pitcher ſhall be broken, and I ſhall be with my God, and ſee ſuch glory which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable; When his neighbours ſtanding by, ſeeing him ſo willing and deſirous to dye, told him that God had no need of him in heaven, but they had need of him on earth; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, True, ſaith he, God nath no need of me, but I have need of him, and he will glorifie me. He would often ſpeak with much admiration and affection of Gods goodneſs to him in dealing ſo graciouſly and favourably with him in the time of his ſickneſs, and profeſſed that he thought that God laid him as ſoftly in the grave as ever he laid any man. Oh ſaid he to the ſtanders by, Walke cloſe with God, he can do you a good turne when you come to dye. Well, gone he is, God looks for improvement of loſses as well as of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſearch out thoſe ſins which have made God to take him away from your heads, be humbled for them, caſt them away, that God may look down graciouſly upon you, viſit you in mercy, ſend you a Paſtor after his own heart, and that a double portion of that ſpirit which was upon your never to be forgotten Father and inſtructer may reſt upon his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117061:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
